Inventory of the Norris E. Dodd papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Norris E. Dodd papers
1905-1969
1946-1953
75020
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 13 oversize boxes, 4 linear ft (13.4 linear feet)
Collection includes notebooks, travel documents, speeches and writings, photographs, audiovisual material, and memorabilia, relating to American and world agricultural problems during 1905 to 1969.
Dodd, Norris E., 1879-1968.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into five series: Personal papers file, Published writings file, Photographs/Negatives, Memorabilia and Sound Recordings. Materials there after arranged by subject.
Biographical Note
July 20, 1879 Born, Chichsaw County, Iowa
1900-1907 Opened and operated drug stores in Pendleton, Pilot Rock, Baker, Haines, and Wallowa, Oregon
1907-1912 Built and operated rural and city telephone lines, Haines, Oregon
1933 Chariman, County Wheat Committee, Oregon
1934 Chairman, County Corn-Hog State Board Control, Oregon
1934-1935 Chairman, Corn-Hog State Board Control, Oregon
1936-1937 Chairman, Oregon State Agriculture Conservation Committee
1938-1939 Assistant Director, Western Division, Agriculture Adjustment Agency
1939-1943 Director, Western Division, Agricultural Adjustment Agency
1943-1946 Chief, Agricultural Adjustment Agency
1946-1948 United States Under Secretary of Agriculture
1948-1954 Director-General, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
1968 Died, Arizona
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection dates 1905 to 1969 and documents Dodd’s days as Director-General of the United Nation Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). Collection includes notebooks, travel documents, speeches and writings, photographs, memorabilia, and audiovisual material (10.5" reels) relating to American and world agricultural problems. Series one includes documents related to Dodd's time with the FAO. Series two consist of books with written contributions from Dodd. Series three combines photographs and negatives to showcase the agricultural landscape and harvests from around the world. With a combination of medals and displays of gratitude, series four consist of Dodd’s memorabilia. The sound recordings include magnetic tapes and vinyls relaed to FAO events.
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations.; United Nations--Economic assistance.; United States. Dept. of Agriculture.; Agriculture--United States.; Agriculture.; Food supply.; International agricultural cooperation.
- Personal papers file, 1935-1969
  Scope and Contents
  Materials include speeches, biographical notes, appointment books, notepads, travel documents and various Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) papers spanning 1935 to 1969. Majority of the collection includes materials from Dodds appointment as Director-General of the United Nation FAO. Representation of Dodd’s travels is documented through reports and notes. Notepads and appointments books provide a glimpse into the position as Director-General of the FAO.
  - Biography, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - FAO Speeches, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Speeches, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Speeches, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Speeches, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Honors and Awards, 1946-1955 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Travel Reports, 1949, 1952 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Letters from N.E. Dodd, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 83rd Congressional Report, 1954 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - FAO Papers, 1948-1965 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Canada and FAO Short History, 1961 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Travel Itinerary and Notes, 1946-1961 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - World Wheat and AAA Ledger, 1935 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Appointment Book, 1950 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Appointment Book, 1951 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Appointment Book, 1952 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Appointment Book, 1953 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Survey Maps, undated (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Passports, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Association Cards, 1949-1969 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Notepads, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Notepads, 1949 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Notepads, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Notepads, 1952 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Notepads, 1953 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Norris E. Dodd Medical Remedies, circa 1905 (Box-folder 5:4)
- Published Writings file, 1953-1955
  - The United Nation FAO, 1953 (Box-folder 5:5-6)
  - So Bold An Aim, 1955 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1941-1960
  Includes photographs, negatives, and glass enclosed negatives dating 1941 to 1958. Photographs and negatives showcase the different agricultural regions Dodd visited. Further the photographs capture pivotal moments in Dodd's life. Negatives capture the agricultural landscape from countries around the world. Majority of photographs are compiled into separate photo albums. Loose photographs have been removed throughout the collection and combined into one box
  - Negatives, 1941-1958
    - U.S., Australia, Germany, Ethiopia, and Rome, 1941 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - U.S. and Germany, 1948 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - France, 1949 (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Italy and Africa, 1949 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Round Up Celebration and Siam, 1949 (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Ecuador, Spain, Turkey, and Round Up, 1949 (Box-folder 6:6)
    - India, Decca, and Pakistan, 1949 (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Liberia and Ethiopia, 1950 (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Canada, 1950 (Box-folder 6:9)
    - South America, 1950 (Box-folder 6:10-11)
    - South America and Africa, 1950 (Box-folder 6:12-13)
    - South Africa and Canada, 1950 (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Buenos Aires, Moutevideo, and Niagra Falls, 1950 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Germany, Ireland, Belgium, Denmark, Canal Zone, and Holland, 1950 (Box-folder 6:16)
    - Ecuador and Poland, 1950 (Box-folder 6:17)
    - England, Australia, and Italy, 1950 (Box-folder 6:18)
    - Egypt, Hawaii, and Siam, 1950 (Box-folder 6:19)
    - Burma, Laos, and Indonesia, 1950 (Box-folder 6:20)
    - Austria, Korea, and Siam, 1950 (Box-folder 6:21)
    - Oregon, Haines, and Bryce Canyon, 1950 (Box-folder 7:1)
    - United States, 1950 (Box-folder 7:2)
    - India, 1950 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Cuba, 1950 (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Ecuador and Bolivia, 1950 (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Portugal, 1950 (Box-folder 7:6)
    - Hawaii and Bolivia, 1950 (Box-folder 7:7)
    - Asia and Egypt, 1951 (Box-folder 7:8)
    - Iceland, Holland, India, and Greece, 1952 (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Thailand, 1952 (Box-folder 7:10)
    - Austria and Israel, 1952 (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Cerro Jachia and Peru, 1953 (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Austria and France, 1953 (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Italy and Morocco, 1953 (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Siam, 1949-1953 (Box-folder 7:15)
    - Rabat, Morocco, 1953 (Box-folder 7:16)
    - Switzerland, 1953 (Box-folder 7:17)
    - Phoenix and U.S., 1958 (Box-folder 7:18)
    - Phoenix and Mt. Shasta, 1958 (Box-folder 7:19)
    - Africa, Rome, and Asia, undated (Box-folder 7:20)
    - Glass enclosed negatives, unidentified countries, circa 1950 (Box 8-9)
    - Glass enclosed negatives, identified countries, circa 1950 (Onshelf /4 linear feet)
      Housed in three negative cases. May not be used without permission of the Archivist.
  - Photographs, 1941-1960
    - Afghanistan project from the combined Austrian Scythe Manufactures, 1941-1958 (Box 10)
    - The Forestry Invertment-Program of Austria in pictures, 1941-1958 (Box 11)
    - Norris Dodd Photo Album, 1941-1958 (Box 12)
    - Election of Dodd as FAO Director, 1948 (Box 12)
    - Rice in Madras, 1941-1958 (Box 13)
    - Agriculture collections throughout the World, 1941-1958 (Box 13)
    - Pope John XXIII Knight Commander Grand Cross of Saint Sylvester, 1941-1958 (Box 13)
    - Western Region Farm Land, 1941-1958 (Box 14)
    - War Zone, 1941-1958 (Box 14)
    - Agriculture photo album, 1948 (Box 15)
    - Morocco Photographs, 1941-1958 (Box 15)
    - Paraguay Photographs, 1941-1958 (Box 15)
    - Loose Photographs, 1941-1958 (Box 16)
    - Austria Trip and Retirement Scrapbook, 1953-1954 (Box 17)
    - Knight Commander of St. Sylvester Scrapbook, 1958-1960 (Box 17)
    - University of the Pacific Scrapbook, 1948-1958 (Box 18)
    - Mr. Dodd and his Japan Suite, 1952 (Box 19)
    - Travels around the world, 1952-1953 (Box 19)
    - Agriculture Adjustment Agency Scrapbook, 1943-1946 (Box 20)
- Memorabilia, 1946-1955
  Includes signature books, medals, scrapbooks, certificates, ceremonial attire and a bronze sculpture dating 1941 to 1955. Series highlights the career of Norris E. Dodd as Director-General of the FAO. The medals represent honors presented to Dodd for the work throughout his career, including the Grand Cross of Saint Sylvester. Signature books, notebooks and certificates illustrate the gratitude of Dodd's dedication to the FAO with a series of personal messages.
  - Signature Book, 1946 (Box-folder 21:1)
  - Notebooks, 1949, 1955 (Box-folder 21:2)
  - Signature Book, 1954 (Box-folder 21:3-4)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box-folder 21:4)
  - Medals, circa 1950 (Box 22-23)
  - Ceremonial Sash, undated (Boxes 24)
  - Neckpiece, undated (Box 24)
  - Certificates, 1953 (Box 24)
  - Scroll, 1953 November
    Scroll presented to Dodd at the United Nations Food and Agriculture Conference in Rome, Italy.
  - Norris Dodd Bronze Head, undated (Box 27)
- Sound Recordings, 1953-1955
  Includes eight 10.5" magnetic reels and six vinyls. Topics includes FAO confernce, speeches, and celebratory events.
  - Magnetic Reels (10.5" reels), 1954 (Box 25)
  - Vinyls, 1953-1955 (Box 26)